{
  "title": "Algorithms - Recurrence_Relation — Slot 1 (15 Questions)",
  "duration": 42,
  "sections": [
    {
      "name": "Recurrence_Relation — Slot 1",
      "questions": [
        {
          "id": 1,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following recurrence relation:\n<br><br>\n\\(T(n) = 2T(n-1) + n2^n \\quad \\text{for} \\quad n &gt; 0, \\quad T(0) = 1\\)\n<br><br>\nWhich ONE of the following options is CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2025 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(T(n) = \\Theta(n^2 2^n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n) = \\Theta(n 2^n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(T(n) = \\Theta((\\log n)^2 2^n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(T(n) = \\Theta(4^n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(T(n) = \\Theta(n^2 2^n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/460070/gate-cse-2025-set-1-question-10#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 2,
          "question": "<p>Let \\( T(n) \\) be the recurrence relation defined as follows:\n<br> \\(\n\\begin{aligned}\n&amp; T(0)=1, \\\\\n&amp; T(1)=2, \\text { and } \\\\\n&amp; T(n)=5 T(n-1)-6 T(n-2) \\text { for } n \\geq 2\n\\end{aligned}\n\\) <br>Which one of the following statements is TRUE? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\( T(n)=\\Theta\\left(2^n\\right)  \\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\( T(n)=\\Theta\\left(n 2^n\\right)  \\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\( T(n)=\\Theta\\left(3^n\\right)  \\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\( T(n)=\\Theta\\left(n 3^n\\right)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\( T(n)=\\Theta\\left(2^n\\right)  \\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422892/gate-cse-2024-set-2-question-5#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 3,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following recurrence relation:\n<br> \\(\nT(n)=\\left\\{\\begin{array}{c}\n\\sqrt{n} T(\\sqrt{n})+n \\text { for } n \\geq 1, \\\\\n1 \\quad \\text { for } n=1 .\n\\end{array}\\right.\n\\) <br>Which one of the following options is CORRECT? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2024 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>T(n)=\\Theta(n \\log \\log n)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>T(n)=\\Theta(n \\log n)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>T(n)=\\Theta\\left(n^2 \\log n\\right)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>T(n)=\\Theta\\left(n^2 \\log \\log n\\right)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>T(n)=\\Theta(n \\log \\log n)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/422810/gate-cse-2024-set-1-question-32#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 4,
          "question": "<p>For constants \\(a\\geq 1\\) and \\(b \\gt 1\\), consider the following recurrence defined on the non-negative integers:\n<br><br>\n\\(T(n) = a \\cdot T \\left(\\dfrac{n}{b} \\right) + f(n)\\)\n<br><br>Which one of the following options is correct about the recurrence \\(T(n)\\)? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>if \\(f(n)\\) is \\(n \\log_2(n)\\), then \\(T(n)\\) is \\(\\Theta(n \\log_2(n))\\).</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>if \\(f(n)\\) is \\(\\dfrac{n}{\\log_2(n)}\\), then \\(T(n)\\) is \\(\\Theta(\\log_2(n))\\).</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>if \\(f(n)\\) is \\(O(n^{\\log_b(a)-\\epsilon})\\) for some \\(\\epsilon \\gt 0\\), then \\(T(n)\\) is \\(\\Theta(n ^{\\log_b(a)})\\).</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>if \\(f(n)\\) is \\(\\Theta(n ^{\\log_b(a)})\\), then \\(T(n)\\) is \\(\\Theta(n ^{\\log_b(a)})\\).</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>if \\(f(n)\\) is \\(O(n^{\\log_b(a)-\\epsilon})\\) for some \\(\\epsilon \\gt 0\\), then \\(T(n)\\) is \\(\\Theta(n ^{\\log_b(a)})\\).</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357501/gate-cse-2021-set-2-question-39#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 5,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following recurrence relation.<br>\n\\(T\\left ( n \\right )=\\left\\{\\begin{array} {lcl} T(n/2)+T(2n/5)+7n &amp; \\text{if} \\; n &gt; 0\\\\1 &amp; \\text{if}\\; n=0 \\end{array}\\right.\\)<br>\nWhich one of the following options is correct? <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2021 SET-1)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=\\Theta (n^{5/2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=\\Theta (n \\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=\\Theta (n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=\\Theta ((\\log n)^{5/2})\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=\\Theta (n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/357421/gate-cse-2021-set-1-question-30#a_list_title\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 6,
          "question": "<p>The master theorem <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>assumes the subproblems are unequal sizes</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>can be used if the subproblems are of equal size</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>cannot be used for divide and conquer algorithms</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>cannot be used for asymptotic complexity analysis</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>can be used if the subproblems are of equal size</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/331325/isro2020-21\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 7,
          "question": "<p>For parameters a and b, both of which are \\(\\omega(1) , T(n)=T(n^{1/a})+1\\), and \\(T(b)=1\\). Then \\(T(n)\\) is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2020)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\log _a \\log_b n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\log _{ab} n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\log _b \\log_a n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\log _2 \\log_2 n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\Theta (\\log _a \\log_b n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/333229/gate2020-cs-2#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 8,
          "question": "<p>The running time of an algorithm is given by:<br>\\(T(n)=\\left\\{\\begin{matrix} T(n-1)+T(n-2)-T(n-3), &amp;\\text {  if } n&gt;3\\\\  n, &amp;\\text{  otherwise}\\end{matrix}\\right.\\)<br>Then what should be the relation between \\(T(1),T(2),T(3)\\), so that the order of the algorithm is constant? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2018)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>T(1) = T(2) = T(3)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>T(1) + T(3) = 2T(2)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>T(1) - T(3) = T(2)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>T(1) + T(2) = T(3)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>T(1) = T(2) = T(3)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/213551/isro2018-37\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 9,
          "question": "<p>The recurrence relation that arises in relation with the complexity of binary search is: <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2017)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=2 T\\left(\\frac{n}{2}\\right)+k, \\mathrm{k} \\text { is a constant }\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=T\\left(\\frac{n}{2}\\right)+k, \\mathrm{k} \\text { is a constant }\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=T\\left(\\frac{n}{2}\\right)+\\log n\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=T\\left(\\frac{n}{2}\\right)+n\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=T\\left(\\frac{n}{2}\\right)+k, \\mathrm{k} \\text { is a constant }\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2444/gate1994-1-7-isro2017-14\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 10,
          "question": "<p>Consider the recurrence function <br> \\(T(n)=\\left\\{\\begin{matrix} 2T(\\sqrt{n})+1, &amp; n \\gt 2\\\\ 2,&amp; 0 \\lt n\\leq 2 \\end{matrix}\\right.\\) <br>Then T(n) in terms of   \\(\\theta\\)   notation is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2017 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (log log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\theta  (logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (\\sqrt{n})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\theta  (n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\theta  (logn)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0.67,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/118623/gate2017-2-30#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 11,
          "question": "<p>Consider the following recurrence:<br>\\(T(n)=2T\\left ( \\sqrt{n}\\right )+1, T(1)=1\\)<br>Which one of the following is true? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2016)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=\\Theta (\\log\\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=\\Theta (\\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=\\Theta (\\sqrt{n})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=\\Theta (n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(T(n)=\\Theta (\\log n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1829/gate2006-51-isro2016-34\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 12,
          "question": "<p>Suppose you want to move from 0 to 100 on the number line. In each step, you either move right by a unit distance or you take a shortcut. A shortcut is simply a pre-specified pair of integers i,j with \\(i \\lt j\\). Given a shortcut i, j if you are at position i on the number line, you may directly move to j. Suppose T(k) denotes the smallest number of steps needed to move from k to 100. suppose further that there is at most 1 shortcut involving any number, and in particular from 9 there is a shortcut to 15. Let y and z be such that T(9) = 1 + min(T(y), T(z)). Then the value of the product yz is_______. <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-3)</strong></p>",
          "type": "numeric",
          "options": [],
          "correct_answer": "150",
          "marks": 2,
          "negative_marks": 0,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/2071/gate2014-3-37#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 13,
          "question": "<p>Which one of the following correctly determines the solution of the recurrence relation with\nT(1) = 1? <br> \\(T(n)=2T(\\frac{n}{2})+logn\\) <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2014 SET-2)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n logn)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n^{2})\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (log n)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(\\theta (n)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/1968/gate2014-2-13#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 14,
          "question": "<p>The recurrence relation capturing the optimal execution time of the Towers of Hanoi problem with n discs is <br><br><strong>(GATE CSE 2012)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>T(n) = 2T(n - 2) + 2</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>T(n) = 2T(n - 1) + n</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>T(n) = 2T(n/2) + 1</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>T(n) = 2T(n - 1) + 1</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>D.</b> <p>T(n) = 2T(n - 1) + 1</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/48/gate2012-16#a_list\" targer=\"_blank\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        },
        {
          "id": 15,
          "question": "<p>Let \\(T(n)\\) be defined by \\(T(1)=10\\) and \\(T(n+1)=2n+T(n)\\) for all integers \\(n \\geq 1\\). Which of the following  represents the order of growth of \\(T(n)\\) as a function of n? <br><br><strong>(ISRO CSE 2011)</strong></p>",
          "type": "single",
          "options": [
            "<b>A.</b> <p>\\(O(n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>B.</b> <p>\\(O(n \\log n)\\)</p>",
            "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O(n^2)\\)</p>",
            "<b>D.</b> <p>\\(O(n^3)\\)</p>"
          ],
          "correct_answer": "<b>C.</b> <p>\\(O(n^2)\\)</p>",
          "marks": 1,
          "negative_marks": 0.33,
          "explanation": "<a href=\"https://gateoverflow.in/47492/isro2011-56\" target=\"_blank\" rel=\"noopener\">Click here for detail solution by gateoverflow</a>"
        }
      ]
    }
  ]
}